Finding Aid for Women's Research Club (University of Michigan) records, 1902-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Women's Research Club (University of Michigan) records 1902-1999
Women's Research Club (University of Michigan)
88107 Bimu M1 2
The Women's Research Club of the University of Michigan was founded in 1902 in response to the exclusion of women from the recently established all-male research clubs. Records include minutes, correspondence and reports of club officers and committees, papers concerning the club anniversaries, and photographs.
3.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor No. 3338 ) has come to the library in periodic accessions.
No further additions to the records expected.
The records are open to research.
The Women's Research Club of the University of Michigan was founded in 1902 by a group of eight women who had been excluded from the other recently established all-male faculty research clubs (Senior Research Club and Junior Research Club). The first constitution defined the organization's purpose as an association of women for the promotion and encouragement of original research. Active dues paying members were required to present a report about their research at least once a year during one of the monthly meetings. Initially membership was limited to women working in the sciences but was soon widened to include women researchers in all fields. Ultimately membership was expanded to include women staff members, visiting professors or scholars, faculty wives, graduate students, and distinguished scholars who published research or significant critical studies, or who carried on active research in the arts, sciences or humanities. In 1921 the Women's Research Club created a loan fund to provide interest-free loans to women researchers.
Transformations such as the opening of the once all-male Research Club and Science Research Club (known as Junior Research Club until 1945) to women members in the 1970s brought about changes within the Women's Research Club. In 1973 men were made eligible for membership and the first male member joined in 1975. The two groups began holding annual joint meetings and occasionally discussed merging although the Women's Research Club repeatedly voted to remain autonomous.
By the 1990s both the Research Club and Women's Research Club faced decreasing attendance at meetings and difficulties in finding new leadership. Both clubs operated jointly in a loose confederation in the late 1990s before the Women's Research Club members voted for dissolution in 1999. Regular activities ceased on May 31, 1999. Funds from the club's bank accounts were turned over to the university administered Women's Research Club Loan Fund.
For additional history and background, including a list of all known presentation topics and selected reprints researchers may wish to consult the 1992 publication: Ninety Years with the Women's Research Club, University of Michigan: A Retrospective, edited by Marilyn Rosenthal and Ruth Brend. Researchers may also be interested in the records of the University of Michigan Research Club and Science Research Club (originally known as the Junior Research Club) which are also available in the Bentley Library.
Records of the Women's Research Club include minutes, 1902-1999; correspondence, 1903-1939 and 1952-1994; membership lists 1904-1999; financial records 1903-1999; correspondence and reports of club officers and committees, including Loan Fund materials; papers concerning the 25th, 50th, 75th, 85th and 90th anniversaries; relationships with the men’s research club; histories, memorials, photographs, and clippings. The Women's Research Club record group is arranged in seven series partially based on club functions and activities: Historical, Minutes, Correspondence, Membership, Executive Board, Activities, and Anniversaries.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Faculty.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.; Women's Research Club (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Research Club.; University of Michigan--Research.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan--Faculty.; Women college teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; College teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women's Research Club (University of Michigan)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Historical
  The Historical series contains information that conveys an overall perspective of the organization. Material includes various histories, constitutions and amendments as well as information on the 1999 dissolution of the organization.
  - Histories of the Women's Research Club (Box 1)
  - Constitutions, Bylaws, Amendments and Other Legal Papers (Box 1)
  - Constitutional Revision 1973-1985 (Box 1)
  - Constitutional Revision 1996 (Box 1)
  - General Information 1980, undated (Box 1)
  - Publicity and Newspaper Clippings (Box 1)
  - Dissolution of Women's Research Club 1996-1999 (Box 1)
- Minutes of Monthly Meetings
  The Minutes series contains the minutes of the general meeting of the WRC from 1902 to 1999. The minutes of Executive Board meetings are kept within the Executive Board series but researchers will find some Executive Board material interspersed among the general minutes, particularly for the years prior to 1970. Minutes of the general meetings typically include announcements, committee reports, membership information, and background about speakers and their topics.
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1902-1910 (Box 1)
  - 1910-1912 (Box 1)
  - 1914-1924 (Box 1)
  - 1925-1932 (Box 1)
  - 1932-1937 (Box 1)
  - 1937-1947 (Box 1)
  - 1947-1954 (Box 1)
  - 1954-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1959-1966 (Box 1)
  - 1966-1970 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1979 (Box 1)
  - 1980-1989 (Box 1)
  - 1990-1999 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series contains letters pertaining to general club activities as well as event planning and membership issues. Occasional non-correspondence background material is interspersed within this series which covers the period from 1903 to 1994. One folder relates to correspondence regarding the Research Club and Science Research Club from 1938 to 1972.
  - General
    - 1903-1909 (Box 1)
    - 1910-1929 (Box 1)
    - 1930-1939 (Box 1)
    - 1952-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1985 (Box 2)
    - 1986-1994 (Box 2)
  - Research Club and Science Research Club 1938-1972 (Box 2)
- Membership
  The Membership series contains lists compiled annually of the club's members including letters of invitation, applications, nominations, and questionnaires. It contains records from 1902 to 1999. One folder pertains to honorary membership for Alice Hamilton (MD, Michigan, 1893) and also includes memorial tributes to members Orma Fitch Butler, Lydia Dewitt, Lilly Melchior Roberts, and Adelia Marie Beeuwkes.
  - Address Lists 1963-1981, undated (some gaps) (Box 2)
  - Membership Nominations 1953-1991, undated (Box 2)
  - Fall Letter to Members and Annual Questionnaires 1958-1998 undated. (Box 2)
  - Membership Lists
    - 1904-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1970-1978 (Box 2)
    - 1979-1985, 1 floppy disks 5.25" (Box 2)
      (includes one 5 1/4" computer disk)
    - 1985-1998 (Box 2)
  - Member Handbooks 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Honorary Membership for Alice Hamilton and Memorials (Box 2)
- Executive Board
  The Executive Board series contains material relating to the meetings of the officers of the WRC. This includes minutes, handbooks, reports, and information on the loan fund. The reports from the treasurer are particularly prominent in the series. The series dates from 1903 to 1999. Minutes from the 1990s reflect the discussions of the organization's future and ultimate dissolution. Additional Executive Board minutes also appear within the Minutes series.
  - Minutes and Agendas
    - 1963-1973 (Box 2)
    - 1976-1980 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1984, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1985-1990 (Box 2)
    - 1991-1995 (Box 2)
    - 1996-1999 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - Nominating Reports 1962-1975 (Box 2)
  - Lists of Officers and Committees 1932-1999 (Box 2)
  - Officers Handbooks
    - 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Vice President, Reports and Miscellaneous 1965-1973 (Box 2)
  - Treasurer
    - Treasurer's Books
      - 1903-1954 (Box 3)
      - 1954-1971 (Box 3)
      - 1971-1973 (Box 3)
      - 1993-1999 (Box 3)
    - Reports and Miscellaneous
      - 1938-1981 (Box 3)
      - 1979-1995 (Box 3)
    - Income Tax Materials
      - 1962-1969 (Box 3)
      - 1981-1982 (Box 3)
    - Auditing Committee Reports and Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Loan Fund
      - Correspondence with Recipients, Alphabetically Arranged (Box 3)
      - Correspondence and Reports 1925-1982 (Box 3)
      - Administration
        - 1979-1980 (Box 3)
        - 1981-1992 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous 1973-1986 (Box 3)
- Activities
  The Activities series primarily consists of information about talks presented to the club. A folder labeled, "Historical Record, 1902-1974" provides a compiled list of all the presentations within that time period. Audio cassette tapes of three lectures given in 1978 are in this series. The series covers 1904-1999.
  - Audio Tapes of lectures, 3 audiocassettes
    - "The Child in Medieval Art," April 3, 1978 by Ilene Forsyth (Box 3)
    - "Solar Activity-1978," September 11, 1978 by Helen Dodson Prince (Box 3)
    - "Comic Characters in Tales of High Adventure," November 6, 1978 by Martha Kreig (Box 3)
  - Talks
    - Historical Record 1902-1974 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Activities
      - 1974-1980 (Box 3)
      - 1981-1988 (Box 3)
    - Abstracts of Papers Presented 1903-1921 (Box 3)
    - Information about Speakers and Topics 1970-1999, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Women's Rights Committee, Reports and Clippings 1972 (Box 3)
- Anniversaries
  Material commemorating various anniversary celebrations is found within the Anniversaries series. It includes material from the 25th, 50th, 75th, 85th and 90th anniversary celebrations. Photographs from the 75th and 85th celebrations are in this series. The series dates from 1929 to 1991. An autograph book from 1929 contains signatures of all members present at the 25th anniversary banquet. Information sheets inviting members to the banquet also contain information on activities and research since election to the WRC. These forms provide an interesting glimpse of the achievements and contributions of the members through 1929.
  - 1929 Autograph Book and Membership Information (Box 3)
  - 1929, 1952 Correspondence and Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - 75th Anniversary 1977
    - Award Banquet and Reception (Box 4)
    - Celebration Award Recipients (Box 4)
    - Committee Meetings (Box 4)
    - Correspondence (Box 4)
    - Funding (Box 4)
    - Guest Register and Program (Box 4)
    - Historical Review Questionnaire (Box 4)
    - Invitations (Box 4)
    - Photographs (Box 4)
    - Publicity (Box 4)
  - 85th Anniversary 1988-1989 (Box 4)
  - 90th Anniversary 1991 (Box 4)